A Guide to the Nancy Ridley Pretlow Bozarth Papers, 1896-1989
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Nancy Ridley Pretlow Bozarth Papers, 1896-1989
The Library of Virginia
45500
8.7 cubic feet (20 boxes).
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no access restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Lyndon H. Hart III, Richmond.
Biographical Information
Nancy Ridley Pretlow was born in Portsmouth, Virginia on 20 October 1901. She was the daughter of Charles Fox Pretlow, Jr. (1872-1937) and Ann Eliza Ridley (1875-1915). She attended Stuart Hall and the College of William and Mary. Pretlow married Walter Fortiner Bozarth (1900-1955) on 27 August 1925 in Roanoke County, Virginia. They resided in Williamburg, Virginia, where she was an employee of the Colonial Williamsburg Foundation in their information center and hostess department. After her retirement, she was a docent at Bruton Parish Church, and she traveled extensively in Europe. Nancy Ridley Pretlow Bozarth died on 19 January 1988, and is buried in Williamsburg Memorial Park.
Scope and Content
Papers, 1896-1989, of Nancy Ridley Pretlow Bozarth (1901-1988) of Williamsburg, Virginia, containing correspondence and subject files. Much of the collection relates to the military service of her husband Walter Fortiner Bozarth (1900-1954) with the 1315th Engineer Construction Battalion during World War II, and also her later interest in foreign travel.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged into the following series:
Series I. Correspondence.
Series II. Subject Files.
Contents List
- Series I. Correspondence., Extent: 6 boxes. (Box 1-6)
  The earliest correspondece includes letters between Nancy Ridley Pretlow and Walter F. Bozarth around the time of their marriage in 1925. There are also letters written to her by her father Charles F. Pretlow, Jr. (1872-1937) in Pittsburgh. Subjects include courtship and marriage, visits, health, travel, weather, and the birth of their daughters Nancy Pretlow Bozarth (b. 1927) and Elizabeth Ridley Bozarth (1930-1976). There is a large amount of correspondence related to Walter F. Bozarth's military service with the 1315th Engineer Construction Battalion during World War II. The letters are written to his his wife and daughters while he was attending engineer school at Fort Belvoir, Virignia, and then when he was stationed at Camp Claiborne, Louisiana and Camp Sutton, North Carolina. Bozarth suffered injuries in a Jeep accident in May 1944, and many of the letters were written while he was recuperating at Moore General Hospital in Swannanoa, North Carolina. The post-1955 correspondence contains mainly postcards and letters written by Nancy Bozarth to her daughters and their families while she was traveling in the United States and Europe. A majority of the correspondence was transcribed by Lyndon H. Hart III (b. 1953), and are included with the originals.
  - 1896. (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - 1914. (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - 1919. (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - 1920. (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - 1923. (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - 1924. (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - 1925 (February). (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - 1925 (August). (Box 1, Folder 8-12)
  - 1925 (November). (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - 1927. (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - 1928. (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - 1933. (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - 1935. (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - 1936. (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - 1937 (February-October). (Box 1, Folder 19-21)
  - 1937 (November-December). (Box 2, Folder 1-3)
  - 1938. (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - 1939. (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - 1941. (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - 1943 (May-August). (Box 2, Folder 7-15)
  - 1943 (September) - 1944 (March). (Box 3, Folder 1-13)
  - 1944 (April-September). (Box 4, Folder 1-12)
  - 1944 (October). (Box 5, Folder 1-3)
  - 1949. (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - 1950. (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - 1951. (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - 1952 (March-April). (Box 5, Folder 7-10)
  - 1953. (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - 1954 (April-December). (Box 5, Folder 12-14)
  - 1955 (January). (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - 1955 (March-April). (Box 5, Folder 16-18)
  - 1955 (May-June). (Box 6, Folder 1-2)
  - 1956. (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - 1957. (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - 1958 (August). (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - 1959-1965. (Box 6, Folder 6-12)
  - 1967-1971. (Box 6, Folder 13-17)
  - 1973. (Box 6, Folder 18)
  - 1976-1977. (Box 6, Folder 19-20)
  - 1980. (Box 6, Folder 21)
  - 1985-1986. (Box 6, Folder 22-23)
  - Undated. (Box 6, Folder 24)
- Series II. Subject Files., Extent: 15 boxes. (Box 6-20)
  The subject files contain calling cards, clippings, estate papers, greeting cards, home construction and ownership records, invitations, military service records, photographs, postcards, programs, scrapbooks, and sympathy cards and notes. There are materials related to her interest in travel, including brochures and guidebooks, receipts, tickets, expense books, itineraries, and diaries. Also included are materials documenting her career in the hostess department at Colonial Williamsburg. There are also business records concerning Walter Bozarth's career in the lumber business and excavation contracting, and as owner of a television repair shop, including accounts and receipts, licenses, and payroll and tax records.
  - Accounts and Receipts. (Box 6, Folder 25)
  - Accounts and Receipts - Flora W. Bozarth. (Box 6, Folder 26)
  - Addresses. (Box 6, Folder 27)
  - Bank Books. (Box 6, Folder 28)
  - Birth/Marriage/Death Certificates. (Box 6, Folder 29)
  - Birthday List. (Box 6, Folder 30)
  - Bozarth Lumber and Package Corporation. (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Bozarth Lumber and Package Corporation - Employee Payroll/Taxes. (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Brooke. (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Calling Cards. (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Candlestick Drawings/Diagrams. (Box 18, Folder n/a)
  - Check Stubs,1924-1925. (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Check Stubs,1951-1952. (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Clippings. (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - College of William and Mary - Class of 1926. (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Colonial Williamsburg - Historical Information, Handouts. (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Colonial Williamsburg - Hostess Department. (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - Colonial Williamsburg - Publications. (Box 7, Folder 11-12)
  - Confirmation Memorial. (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Cristoforo Colombo (Ship). (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Deeds. (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Diplomas. (Map-case 54, Drawer 10)
  - Drivers Licenses/Vehicle Registrations. (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Escort Record. (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Essays. (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Estate of Flora W. Bozarth. (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Estate of Nancy P. Bozarth. (Box 8, Folder 8-9)
  - Estate of Walter F. Bozarth. (Box 8, Folder 10)
  - Estate of Philip Wallace Hiden. (Box 8, Folder 11)
  - Excavation and Sewer Contractor - Accounts and Receipts. (Box 8, Folder 12-16)
  - Excavation and Sewer Contractor - Licenses, Taxes, Correspondence. (Box 8, Folder 17)
  - Flag - 1315th Engineer Construction Battalion. (Box 18, Folder n/a)
  - Foreign Hotels. (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Foreign Restaurants. (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Foreign Retail Shops. (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Funeral of Walter F. Bozarth. (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Funeral of Betty Bozarth Deal. (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - Funeral of Charles F. Pretlow, Jr. (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - Greeting Cards - Birthday. (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - Greeting Cards - Christmas. (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - Greeting Cards - Easter. (Box 9, Folder 9)
  - Greeting Cards - Get Well. (Box 9, Folder 10-12)
  - Greeting Cards - New Years. (Box 9, Folder 13)
  - Greeting Cards - Thanksgiving. (Box 9, Folder 14)
  - Greeting Cards - Valentines. (Box 9, Folder 15)
  - Gripsholm (Ship). (Box 9, Folder 16)
  - Home Economics Methods Notebook. (Box 9, Folder 17)
  - Invitations, 1916-1919. (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Invitations. (Box 10, Folder 2-3)
  - Kappa Kappa Gamma. (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - Memberships. (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - Memorandum Books. (Box 10, Folder 6-7)
  - Mental Arithmetic by Charles S. Venable. (Box 10, Folder 8)
  - Military Service Benefits. (Box 10, Folder 9)
  - Military Service Records. (Box 10, Folder 10-13)
  - Miscellaneous. (Box 10, Folder 14)
  - Moore General Hospital (Swannanoa, NC). (Box 10, Folder 15)
  - Passport. (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - Photograph - 1315th Engineer Construction Battalion (Map-case 54, Drawer 10)
  - Photographs - Animals/Pets. (Box 19, Folder 1)
  - Photographs - Bozarth Family Group. (Box 19, Folder 2)
  - Photographs - Bozarth, Nancy Ridley Pretlow. (Box 19, Folder 3)
  - Photographs - Bozarth, Walter F. (Box 19, Folder 4)
  - Photographs - Buildings/Places. (Box 19, Folder 5)
  - Photographs - Churches/Cathedrals. (Box 19, Folder 6)
  - Photographs - Deal, Elizabeth Ridley Bozarth. (Box 19, Folder 7)
  - Photographs - European Trips, 1955, 1958. (Box 19, Folder 8)
  - Photographs - Hart Family. (Box 19, Folder 9)
  - Photographs - Kappa Kappa Gamma. (Box 19, Folder 10)
  - Photographs - Model of Jamestowne Candlestick. (Box 19, Folder 11)
  - Photographs - Negatives. (Box 19, Folder 12)
  - Photographs - Oversize. (Box Private Papers Oversize Box 56, Folder n/a)
  - Photographs - People - Miscellaneous. (Box 20, Folder 1)
  - Photographs - "Pokety," Cambridge MD (Edgar Garbisch). (Box 20, Folder 2)
  - Photographs - Pretlow Family. (Box 20, Folder 3)
  - Photographs - Ridley Family. (Box 20, Folder 4)
  - Photographs - Andy Seto/Pao Ling. (Box 20, Folder 5)
  - Photographs - "Sunny Cove," W.F. Bozarth Home, Queen's Lake, Williamsburg, VA. (Box 20, Folder 6)
  - Photographs - Williamsburg/Colonial Williamsburg. (Box 20, Folder 7-9)
  - Photographs - Unidentified - Building/Places. (Box 20, Folder 10-11)
  - Photographs - Unidentified - People. (Box 20, Folder 12)
  - Poetry/Lyrics. (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - Postcards - Chicago. (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - Postcards - Florida. (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - Postcards - Georgia. (Box 11, Folder 5)
  - Postcards - London. (Box 11, Folder 6)
  - Postcards - Massachusetts. (Box 11, Folder 7)
  - Postcards - Mississippi. (Box 11, Folder 8)
  - Postcards - New York. (Box 11, Folder 9)
  - Postcards - Virginia. (Box 11, Folder 10)
  - Postcards - Washington, DC. (Box 11, Folder 11)
  - Postcards - Foreign. (Box 11, Folder 12)
  - Postcards - Other States. (Box 11, Folder 13)
  - Postcards - Ships. (Box 11, Folder 14)
  - "The Powder Horn" - Williamsburg High School, 1929. (Box 11, Folder 15)
  - Prescriptions. (Box 11, Folder 16)
  - Programs. (Box 11, Folder 17-18)
  - Programs. (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - Programs - Foreign Trips. (Box 12, Folder 2)
  - Queen Elizabeth (Ship). (Box 12, Folder 3)
  - Queens Lake Club. (Box 12, Folder 4)
  - Queens Lake House - Account Book, 1953. (Box 12, Folder 5)
  - Queens Lake House - Construction Accounts and Receipts. (Box 12, Folder 6-8)
  - Queens Lake House - Equipment Owners Manuals. (Box 12, Folder 9)
  - Queens Lake House - Insurance. (Box 12, Folder 10)
  - Queens Lake House - Plans and Specifications (Map-case 54, Drawer 10)
  - Ration Books and Cards. (Box 12, Folder 11)
  - Receipts - Travel Purchases,1955. (Box 12, Folder 12)
  - Rental Income - Flora W. Bozarth,1951-1952. (Box 12, Folder 13)
  - Report Cards/Graduation Certificates. (Box 12, Folder 14)
  - S.S. United States. (Box 13, Folder 1)
  - St. Christopher's News (Winter 1971). (Box 13, Folder 2)
  - Scrapbooks. (Box 18, Folder n/a)
  - Sterlingwood Woman's Club. (Box 13, Folder 3)
  - Stuart Hall - Class of 1945. (Box 13, Folder 4)
  - Sympathy Cards and Notes - Death of Walter F. Bozarth. (Box 13, Folder 5)
  - Sympathy Cards and Notes - Death of Betty Bozarth Deal. (Box 13, Folder 6-12)
  - Taxes,1950-1952. (Box 14, Folder 1)
  - TV Shop - Bank Book/Cancelled Checks. (Box 14, Folder 2)
  - TV Shop - Construction Accounts and Receipts and Maintenance. (Box 14, Folder 3)
  - TV Shop - Correspondence. (Box 14, Folder 4)
  - TV Shop - Customer Accounts and Receipts. (Box 14, Folder 5)
  - TV Shop - Daybook. (Box 14, Folder 6)
  - TV Shop - Employee Payroll/Taxes. (Box 14, Folder 7)
  - TV Shop - Floor Plan. (Box 14, Folder 8)
  - TV Shop - Inventory. (Box 14, Folder 9)
  - TV Shop - Parts and Supplies - Accounts and Receipts. (Box 14, Folder 10)
  - TV Shop - Plans and Specifications (Map-case 54, Drawer 10)
  - TV Shop - Receipt Book. (Box 14, Folder 11)
  - TV Shop - Stock Certificates. (Box 14, Folder 12)
  - TV Shop - Taxes. (Box 14, Folder 13)
  - Tickets - Foreign Travel and Admissions. (Box 14, Folder 14)
  - Travel Brochures, Guidebooks, etc. - Annapolis. (Box 14, Folder 15)
  - Travel Brochures, Guidebooks, etc. - Belgium. (Box 14, Folder 16)
  - Travel Brochures, Guidebooks, etc. - Copenhagen. (Box 14, Folder 17)
  - Travel Brochures, Guidebooks, etc. - Cuba. (Box 14, Folder 18)
  - Travel Brochures, Guidebooks, etc. - Florida. (Box 14, Folder 19)
  - Travel Brochures, Guidebooks, etc. - France. (Box 14, Folder 20)
  - Travel Brochures, Guidebooks, etc. - Germany. (Box 15, Folder 1)
  - Travel Brochures, Guidebooks, etc. - Gibraltar. (Box 15, Folder 2)
  - Travel Brochures, Guidebooks, etc. - Great Britain. (Box 15, Folder 3-5)
  - Travel Brochures, Guidebooks, etc. - Hungary. (Box 15, Folder 6)
  - Travel Brochures, Guidebooks, etc. - Italy. (Box 15, Folder 7-9)
  - Travel Brochures, Guidebooks, etc. - Miscellaneous. (Box 15, Folder 10)
  - Travel Brochures, Guidebooks, etc. - Mississippi. (Box 15, Folder 11)
  - Travel Brochures, Guidebooks, etc. - New Orleans. (Box 15, Folder 1)
  - Travel Brochures, Guidebooks, etc. - New York. (Box 16, Folder 1)
  - Travel Brochures, Guidebooks, etc. - North Carolina. (Box 16, Folder 2)
  - Travel Brochures, Guidebooks, etc. - Norway. (Box 16, Folder 3)
  - Travel Brochures, Guidebooks, etc. - Paris. (Box 16, Folder 4)
  - Travel Brochures, Guidebooks, etc. - Scotland. (Box 16, Folder 5)
  - Travel Brochures, Guidebooks, etc. - South Carolina. (Box 16, Folder 6)
  - Travel Brochures, Guidebooks, etc. - Spain. (Box 16, Folder 7-8)
  - Travel Brochures, Guidebooks, etc. - Stockholm. (Box 16, Folder 9)
  - Travel Brochures, Guidebooks, etc. - Switzerland. (Box 16, Folder 10)
  - Travel Brochures, Guidebooks, etc. - Virginia. (Box 16, Folder 11)
  - Travel Diary,1955. (Box 16, Folder 12)
  - Travel Diary,1955 - Transcription. (Box 16, Folder 13)
  - Travel Diary,1958. (Box 17, Folder 1)
  - Travel Diary,1958 - Transcription. (Box 17, Folder 2)
  - Travel Expense Book. (Box 17, Folder 3)
  - Travel Expense Book,1937-1938, 1943-1945. (Box 17, Folder 4)
  - Travel Expense Book,1941. (Box 17, Folder 5)
  - Travel Expense Book,1952. (Box 17, Folder 6)
  - Travel Itineraries. (Box 17, Folder 7)
  - Travel Notebook. (Box 17, Folder 8)
  - United Daughters of the Confederacy - Membership Certificate. (Box 18, Folder n/a)
  - Wren Building - William and Mary. (Box 17, Folder 9)